Guide to the Quadrangle Pictures records, 1932-1991
Duke University. University Archives
Quadrangle Pictures records 1932-1991
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Quadrangle Pictures.
1.5 linear feet Extent: 1000 Items
Quadrangle Pictures, also informally known as Q.P, Quad Pics, and Quad Flix, formed in 1928 to screen films on campus. It quickly became the central source of campus entertainment. Materials in the collection range from 1932 to 1991 and include programs, printed matter, annual reports, financial statements, and advertising campaign materials.
UA.09.13.0002
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Quadrangle Pictures records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975-2000.
Historical Note
Quadrangle Pictures, also informally known as Q.P, Quad Pics, and Quad Flix, formed in 1928 to screen films on campus. It quickly became the central source of campus entertainment. Sponsored through the YMCA, it made annual reports to the University Motion Pictures Committee. Walter M. Upchurch, '31, who as a student originally began the film screenings, managed the program from 1931 to 1941.
The program encompassed much more than just films. In its early days, films would be accompanied by newsreels, cartoons, organ concerts, and community sings. On special occasions such as the annual birthday parties, entertainers such as Tommy Dorsey and Benny Goodman brought their musicians and singers to play. Paul Whiteman and his Orchestra even did a live CBS radio broadcast during the tenth birthday event.
In 1933, Upchurch, now also serving as Director of Student Activities, opened "A School of Movie Palace Operation," a non-credit course that allowed students to earn some money while learning the concepts of theater operation. At its height, Quadrangle Pictures had forty uniformed ushers, who marched, drilled, and memorized daily schedules. The "School" closed in 1941.
Page Auditorium was equipped with an organ used to lead organlogues and community sings. The program also sponsored a record lending library that provided to students a large selection of classical recordings. After World War II, there were significant changes in Quadrangle Pictures. Film screenings moved to the weekends, ushers lost their uniforms, and live performances ended. More of the entertainment programming on campus was organized by the Duke University Union, created in 1954.
Quadrangle Pictures became a staff-administered program of the Union, advised by the Duke Film Society, an independent group founded to encourage film appreciation. Screenings of films moved to the Griffith Theater in 1988. In 1991, administration of Quadrangle Pictures passed to Freewater Films, which shows popular films on weekends under the Quad Flix name.
Collection Overview
Materials range from 1932 to 1991 and include subject files, arranged alphabetically, relating to the work and programming of Quadrangle Pictures. The files on advertising campaigns detail the types of advertising done for numerous Quad Pics events, including their annual birthday parties at which famous bands frequently played. These files describe visits by bands such as Paul Whiteman and his Orchestra, Tommy Dorsey, and Benny Goodman. Also included are annual reports by manager Walter M. Upchurch, most of which date from the 1930s. Files of financial statements include budgets, film costs, and some attendance figures. The policies and procedures governing ushers, doormen, and other staff are well documented. Flyers, schedules, and programs including song programs of the organlogues and community sings held at Quadrangle Pictures events are also present.
Subject Headings
Duke University. Freewater Films; Duke University. Office of Student Activities; Duke University. Union; Quadrangle Pictures (Duke University)
Related Material
Division of Student Affairs. Office of Student Activities Records, 1939-1993
University Archives, Duke University.
Katherine M. Banham papers, 1910-1995
University Archives, Duke University.
Motion Pictures Committee, Duke University (small collections)
University Archives, Duke University.
Walter M. Upchurch papers, 1927-1988
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 1 Box
  - Advertising Campaign, Eight Birthday Party, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Advertising Campaign, Dean Hudson and His Orchestra, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Advertising Campaign, Ninth Birthday Party, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Advertising Campaign, Jimmie Lunceford and His Orchestra, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Advertising Campaign, "Trial by Jury", 1938 (Box 1)
  - Advertising Campaign, Tenth Birthday Party, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Advertising Campaign, The Graff Ballet, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Advertising Campaign, Eleventh Birthday Party, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Advertising Campaign, Thirteenth Birthday Party, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report, 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report, 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Articles, 1982-1986 (Box 1)
  - Community Sing, 1930s-1940 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1965 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1975 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, 1980-1984 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Historical Articles, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Organ and Organlogues, 1936-1939 (Box 1)
  - Policies and Procedures, ca. 1939-1942 (Box 1)
  - Printed Matter, 1932-1949 (Box 1)
  - Printed Matter, 1950-1967 (Box 1)
  - Printed Matter, 1971-1991 (Box 1)
  - Schedules, 1971-1985 (Box 1)
  - Schedules, Office of Cultural Affairs, 1981-1989 (Box 1)
  - Suggestions for Improvement, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Summer Pictures, 1971-1985 (Box 1)